{"tossups": [{"question": "These people lived in<em> wharenui</em> or big houses, some of which ban food inside. Nephrite jade weapons called punamu were used by these people, who built a defensive settlement, or Pa, at Mount Eden. Continuation of these people\u2019s<em> tikanga</em>, or customs, may have led to devastating raids into the Bay of Plenty led by Hongi Hika with new found firearms. A subgroup of these people, the Moriori settled in the Chatham Islands, while the main group of these people signed the Treaty of Waitangi. For ten points, name these Polynesian indigenous people of New Zealand.", "answer": "The<b> Maori</b> people", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man supposedly went into battle unprotected, believing that \u201cthe Lord God [was his] armor.\u201dFrench aid in the Treaty of Barwalde allowed this man to launch an intervention in Germany. Chancellor Axel Oxenstierna ruled in place of this man after he was killed leading a cavalry charge at L\u00a8utzen. This father of Christina became known as the \u201cLion of the North\u201d after winning the Battle of Breitenfeld. For ten points, identify this king of Sweden during the Thirty Years\u2019 War.", "answer": "<b> Gustavus Adolphus</b> (accept<b> Gustav II</b> Adolph, prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In Canada, sites for this project included the Eldorado Mine and Chalk River. Dupont\u2019s P-9 Project produced substances for this project, for which Kenneth Nicholas helped buy pitchblende ore from the Belgian Congo. Washington\u2019s Hanford Site was one complex operated by this project, whose final products were designed and tested at a site in New Mexico, Los Alamos. For ten points, name this Allied project to produce the atomic bomb.", "answer": "<b> Manhattan</b> Project Page 1", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In the precursor to this case, Samuel Russell\u2019s testimony was ruled hearsay and he hired Samuel Bay. In this case, 7 justices refused to abide by<em> Marie Louise v. Marot</em> despite the opinion of John McLean. Robert Cooper Grier was pressured by James Buchanan to side with the majority in this case. The majority decision in this case ruled that Congress cannot ban slavery in certain territories as it infringes on the right to property. For ten points, name this 1857 case in which Roger Taney ruled that an enslaved man was not free because he spent time in Wisconsin.", "answer": "Dred<b> Scott</b> v. Sandford", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One historian described this government as \u201cthe past that will not pass\u201d in a book about the memory of this government, titled its \u201cSyndrome.\u201d This government studied by Henry Rousso and Robert Paxton ran the Drancy internment camp and carried out the Vel d\u2019Hiv roundup against its Jewish population. Formed after the Second Armistice at Compi\u00b4egne, for ten points, name this government led by Pierre Laval and Phillip P\u00b4etain which collaborated with the Nazis in WWII.", "answer": "<b> Vichy</b> France", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A racist and comically incompetent former owner of this team names a rule banning NBA teams from trading their first round draft pick from consecutive drafts. Current owner Dan Gilbert wrote a letter in Comic Sans stating that this team will \u201cwin an NBA championship before the self-titled former \u201cKing\u201dwins one.\u201d For ten points, name this team that drafted Anthony Bennett, Andrew Wiggins, and Kyrie Irving while its biggest star, LeBron James, took his four year sabbatical in Miami.", "answer": "<b> Cleveland Cavaliers</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A leader at this location wrote a letter to \u201cAll Americans in the World\u201d in which he claimed he was determined to die like a soldier. James Neill, appalled by the lack of supplies at this location, wrote to the provisional government saying \u201cIf there has ever been a dollar here I have no knowledge of it.\u201d This location was said to be key to keeping \u201cBexar out of the hands of the enemy\u201d in a letter by James Bowie who claimed its defense was necessary for the salvation of Texas. For ten points, name this mission in San Atonio that was besieged by Mexiacn forces.", "answer": "The<b> Alamo</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader won the Battle of Shirimni during his campaigns against the Georgians. After the failed Siege of Sredets, this leader was nearly killed in the Battle of the Gates of Trajan. This leader founded the Varangian Guard after marrying his sister Anna to a foreign leader. This leader\u2019s enemy Samuel suffered a heart attack after this leader blinded 99 of every 100 prisoners from the Battle of Kleidion. For ten points, name this Byzantine Emperor named for his victory over the Bulgarian empire.", "answer": "<b> Basil II</b> (Accept<b> Basil the Bulgar Slayer</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Hobbes argued that complete submission to this model of government is necessary because humans are self-interested. Locke claimed that this model of government prevents a permanent state of war between individuals. One work titled after this model begins \u201cman is born free, but everywhere is in chains\u201d and argues that this model obeys the general will. For ten points, what model where citizens surrender some rights to legitimate government to guarantee others was written about by Rousseau?", "answer": "The<b> Social Contract</b> (accept<b> monarchy</b> or<b> absolutism</b> until \u201cprevents\u201d)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "Juhayman al-Otaybi carried out a terrorist attack in this city at a location that was under renovation by the Binladin group, leading French GIGN commandos to intervene. A Hashimite Sharif who controlled this city, Hussein, led the Arab Revolt and after the fall of the Ottoman Empire, proclaimed himself Caliph. This city\u2019s Banu Quraish forces lost the Battle of Badr to Muslim forces from Medina. For ten points, name this birthplace of Muhammed, where pilgrims travel to do the Hajj.", "answer": "<b> Mecca</b> or<b> Makkah</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In one election, this Presidential candidate\u2019s party was attacked by Samuel D. Burchard as the party of \u201cRum, Romanism, and Rebellion.\u201d This politician won over a large number of Republican voters, which were then labeled mugwumps, due to his opponents stance on the spoils system. This man was accused of having an illegitimate child which led to the chant \u201cMa, Ma, where\u2019s my Pa\u201d to become a key part of the Election of 1884. For ten points, name this politician from Ohio, the only President to have served non-consecutive terms.", "answer": "Grover<b> Cleveland</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A piece in this style phases a 12 beat African bell rhythm between two performers. An aleatoric piece in this style contains 53 short phrases each to be repeated a random number of times. The development of this style is credited to La Monte Young. The \u201choly\u201d type of this style is in works such as<em> Tabula Rasa</em> and<em> Fur Alina</em> by Arvo P\u00a8art. One of the first works in this style is Terry Riley\u2019s<em> In C</em>. For ten points, name this style of music that uses a limited set of material.", "answer": "<b> minimal</b>ism (accept word forms)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "William Yancey spearheaded a platform named for this state that held that the Federal government could not restrict slavery in territories. A ship named for this state was sunk at Cherbourg while under the command of Raphael Semmes and was the subject of a series of claims in which the United States demanded restitution from Great Britain. At a battle in this state, a Union commander ordered \u201cDamn the torpedoes!\u201d en-route to defeating Confederate forces at Mobile Bay. For ten points, name this state that, prior to it being moved to Richmond, hosted the Confederate capital at Montgomery.", "answer": "<b> Alabama</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this period, James McGready organized Kentuckians at the Red River Meeting House. An illiterate speaker named \u201cBlack Harry\u201d preached during this era. Barton Stone\u2019s</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>\u201cNew Lights\u201d movement began during this period. Dispensationalism and Adventism</b> <b>began during this period. Charles Finney coined the term (*)</b> \u201cburned-over district\u201d for western New York during this period. This movement was led by Baptist and Methodist preachers and followed a similarly named movement in the 1730s. For 10 points, name this American religious movement that saw the birth of Mormonism.", "answer": "<b> Second Great Awakening</b> (prompt on \u201cGreat Awakening\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This non-water deity was conflated with the Cretan goddess Britomartis. The destruction of a temple to this deity by Herostratus led to the expression (+) \u201cherostratic fame.\u201d The Brauronia ceremony celebrated this deity. A temple to this deity was destroyed on the same day as Alexander the Great\u2019s birth and was located in (*)</b> Ephesus. This deity sent a wild boar to kill Adonis and turned Actaeon\u2019s hunting dogs against him after he saw her bathing. For 10 points, name this Greek goddess of the hunt, the twin sister of Apollo.", "answer": "<b> Artemis</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s (*) </b>Northern League and Five Star Party formed a government in 2018. For ten points, name this country home to Matteo Salvini and Beppe Grillo.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Italy</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>While serving as military governor of Bavaria, this man compared Nazis to Democrats</b> <b>and Republicans. This man \u201craced to Messina\u201d against (+)</b> <b>Bernard Montgomery after</b> <b>carrying out Operation Husky. This leader commanded the fictional First United States Army Group as part of (*) </b> Operation Fortitude. This general was temporarily removed from command after slapping two shell-shocked solders in 1943. Prior to Operation Overlord, this man gave a series of speeches to his Third Army. For ten points, name this American general nicknamed \u201cOld Blood and Guts.\u201d", "answer": "George S.<b> Patton</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This city names an 1802 poem that opens with a cry for one of its native sons, \u201cthou shouldst be living at this hour.\u201d A poem about this city that opens \u201cI wander thro\u2019 each</b> <b>charter\u2019d street\u201d and describes hearing \u201chow the (+)</b> <b>Chimney-sweepers cry\u201d was written</b> <b>by William Blake. A long poem about this \u201cgrand imperial town\u201d was written by a man who uttered the quip \u201cwhen a man is tired of [this city], he is tired of life\u201d and wrote a (*) </b> <em>Dictionary of the English Language</em>, Samuel Johnson. For ten points, name this city whose modern squalor was captured in T.S. Eliot\u2019s<em> The Waste Land</em>, including its heavily polluted Thames River.", "answer": "<b> London</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b>This man initially refused to attend the Lancaster House peace talks after splitting with a faction led by Reverend Sithole. This man\u2019s government massacred Ndebele civilians as part of the (+) Gukurahundi. This man was opposed by the MDC party which was led by Morgan Tsvangirai. In 1987, this man absorbed Joshua Nkomo\u2019s (*) </b> ZAPU party into this own ZANU party. This man was ousted after a power struggle between his wife Grace and vice-president Emmerson Mnangagwa. Extreme hyperinflation occurred under the leadership of, for ten points, what former dictator of Zimbabwe?", "answer": "Robert<b> Mugabe</b> Page 10", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}